Ellie Taagen

QUANTITATIVE GENETICIST · DATA SCIENTIST · USA & EU CITIZEN

240 Emerson Hall, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, 14853, USA

🛘 +1 (206) 830-0328 | 🔀 et395@cornell.edu | 🌴 etaagen.github.io | 🖸 etaagen | 🛅 ellie-taagen | 💆 @etaagen | given name Ella

Summary_

As a quantitative geneticist, I love to discover the relationships between recombination variation and desirable phenotypes and am driven by their potential to enhance breeding pipeline efficiency and genetic gain. Detail oriented planning and interdisciplinary communication are core pillars of my creative and critical thinking approach to problem solving. I am pursuing a Ph.D. in Plant Genetics at Cornell University with an expected graduation spring 2022, and am drawn to career paths in industry at the intersection of genetics, data science, and molecular biology.

Expertise

Quantitative Genetics
Data Science
Programming
Recombination Science
Molecular Biology

whole genome associations, genomic selection, causal variant identification, multi-omics analysis simulations, reproducible analyses, skillful data visualization, large dataset management (17 Gb) R, Linux, SQL, LaTeX, Git, bioinformatics tools, algorithm workflow development, cloud computing meiosis domain knowledge, controlled recombination mechanisms, applied haplotype breeding experimental design, gene editing domain knowledge, positional cloning, primer optimization multi-disciplinary communication, project management, team leader, creative problem solver

Education

Ph.D. in Plant Genetics Ithaca, NY, USA

CORNELL UNIVERSITY 2017 - May 2022

• Minors: Plant Molecular Biology and International Agriculture and Rural Development

B.S. in Molecular, Cellular, Developmental Biology

University of Washington

• Minor: Nutritional Sciences

Seattle, WA, USA

2012 - 2016

Relevant Experience __

Data Science intern | Genomics Discovery and Application team

Bayer Crop Science

CHARACTERIZING RECOMBINATION RATE VARIATION AND ASSOCIATED HAPLOTYPES

2021 - Present

- · Measuring recombination as a phenotype and applying GWAS to identify haplotypes that may impact recombination in maize cohorts.
- Developing a data set agnostic workflow in order to provide recommendations of haplotype selection, or which controlled recombination technologies to apply.
- · Six-month, full-time position exposure to multi-disciplinary team-based projects and industry-paced research setting.

Ph.D. research | advisor Dr. Jean-Luc Jannink

Cornell University

SIMULATING CONTROLLED RECOMBINATION IN ALLOPOLYPLOID GENOMES

2020 - Present

- Leveraging simulation and bioinformatics tools to better understand controlled recombination's (Taagen et al. 2020) potential to reveal currently inaccessible genetic diversity and innovate increased control over the inheritance of preferred haplotypes.
- Exploring the biological constraints of meiotic recombination, gamete segregation, genome editing, and prediction-based decisions in a plant breeding simulation context.
- Designing novel methods that compare efficiency of cost of traditional breeding to controlled recombination.

Ph.D. research | advisor Dr. Mark Sorrells

Cornell University

IDENTIFYING GENOMIC STRUCTURAL VARIANT BARRIERS TO GENE POSITIONAL CLONING

2017 - 2021

- Applied traditional population development strategies, along with cutting-edge tools in genomics and transcriptomics to better understand
 the landscape of causal variation based breeding decisions. <u>Talk video link</u>, peer feedback: 4.8/5
- Determined that chromosome structural variants can overpower traditional fine-mapping approaches to gene discovery, especially in polyploids, and proposed recommendations for new experimental design standards.
- Results published in (Taagen et al. 2021) and all analysis conducted is reproducible and publicly available as a learning resource at: github.com/etaagen.

Post-baccalaureate RA | advisor Dr. Stephen Jones

Washington State University

BREEDING VALUE CHAIN ENGAGEMENT

2016 - 2017

- Surveyed and engaged supply chain stakeholders and end-users when setting objectives for small grains breeding program.
- Delivered lab and field support for graduate student breeding projects sourced from a broad base of genetic diversity.

November 18, 2021 Ellie Taagen · Résumé

Mentorship & Management

Corteva Agriscience and Cornell School of Integrative Plant Science (SIPS) networking

Virtual

COORDINATOR 2020 - Present

- · Built network and relationship pipeline with Corteva Global Academic Relations Manager and Cornell SIPS industry partnerships liaison.
- · Developed system for matching 50 graduate students with Corteva scientists based on shared career interests.

Diversity and Inclusion Committee, SIPS Cornell

Cornell University

GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE

2020 - 2021

• Facilitate monthly meetings, titled OpenUpSTEM, which provide a space for graduate students to learn about, discuss, and take action towards building a sustainable culture of anti-racism in our community.

Synapsis, Plant Breeding and Genetics GSA

Cornell University

PRESIDENT

2019-2020

- Executed 2020 graduate student recruitment visitation for 15 students.
- Oversaw communication between current plant breeding and genetics students and faculty.

Plant Breeding and Genetics faculty search committee

Cornell University

GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE

2019-2020

- Screened and evaluated 54 applicant packages, and conducted full day interviews with top 3 candidates (research /teaching /chalk-talk).
- · Facilitated graduate student meetings with top candidates and documented graduate student preferences for clear communication to faculty.

Graduate student mentor Cornell University

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTS

2018-2020

- · Hired, trained, and mentored three talented undergraduate research assistants and supervised one honors thesis
- · Coached one graduate school application and interview process, accepted to five plant sciences PhD programs.

Bonsai Professional Coaching Service

Virtual

MENTEE

2018-2020

- Partnered with leadership coach <u>Loriana Sekarski</u> to identify and apply personalized Clifton Strengths by Gallup, top 5 strengths: achiever, learner, analytical, futuristic, individualization.
- Trained in STEM industry professionalism and charted conflict management strategies.

Awards & Scholarships

2022	IWGSC Early Career Award, Plant and Animal Genome conference travel stipend	San Diego, CA
2021	Munger Murphy Graduate Student Award, Cornell PBG	Ithaca, NY
2021	WIT Early Career Award, Borlaug Global Rust Initiative	Virtual
2020	Borlaug Scholar, National Association of Plant Breeders	Virtual
2020	3rd Place , C7 Plant and Animal Genome conference poster competition	San Diego, CA
2019	Awardee, Cornell IARD winter interim travel grant	Kerala, India
2018	Awardee, ASA, CSSA and SSSA Congressional Visit Day travel grant	Washington DC
2018	Future Leader in Science, ASA, CSSA and SSSA	Washington DC

Relevant Workshops_

Enrolled	Data Camp , Python, SQL, Machine Learning	Virtual
2020	Collaborative and Reproducible Data Science in R, NTRES 6940	Cornell University
2019	Linux for Biologists, Institute of Biotechnology	Cornell University
2018	Breeding for Quantitative Traits in Plants, book club facilitator	Cornell University
2017	Tucson Plant Breeding Institute, quantitative genetics bootcamp	Cornell University

Publications.

Taagen, E., J., Gul, A., & Sorrells, M. E. *Positional based cloning "fail-safe" approach is overpowered by wheat (Triticum aestivum) chromosome structural variation.* **(2021)** The Plant Genome

Taagen, E., Bogdanove, A. J. & Sorrells, M. E. Counting on Crossovers: Controlled Recombination for Plant Breeding. **(2020)** <u>Trends in Plant Science</u>

Taagen, E., Bogdanove, A. J. & Sorrells, M. E. *Achieving Controlled Recombination with Targeted Cleavage and Epigenetic Modifiers.* **(2020)** Trends in Plant Science

Sweeney, D. W., Sun, J., **Taagen, E.** & Sorrells, M. E. *Genomic Selection in Wheat.* (Woodhead Publishing. **(2019)** in Applications of Genetic and Genomic Research in Cereals, 273-302